Guide to the Dana Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- James Dwight Dana, 1805-1895; Series I; 5.5 linear feet (20 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - Reusch, Hans, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 96, Reel 3U)
    - Reynolds, J. Emerson, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 96, Reel 3U)
    - Rice, William North, 1881-1882 (Box 3, Folder 96, Reel 3U)
    - Ringgold, Cadwalader, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 96, Reel 3U)
    - Rogers, Henry Darwin, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 97, Reel 3U)
    - Rogers, William Bartin, 1862-1885 (Box 3, Folder 97, Reel 3U)
    - Rosé, W., 1844-1845 (Box 3, Folder 97, Reel 3U)
    - Rowland, [ ____ ], 1879 (Box 3, Folder 97, Reel 3U)
    - Royal Institution of Great Britain, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 97, Reel 3U)
    - Russel, J. C., 1893 (Box 3, Folder 97, Reel 3U)
    - Salisbury, Edward E., 1846 (Box 3, Folder 98, Reel 3U)
    - Saussure, Henri Louis Frederic de, 1857-1860 (Box 3, Folder 98, Reel 3U)
    - Sawkins, James G., 1854-1857 (Box 3, Folder 98, Reel 3U)
    - Scacchi, A., 1846, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 98, Reel 3U)
    - Scheerer, Th., 1850 (Box 3, Folder 98, Reel 3U)
    - Schiaperelli, [ ____ ], 1889 (Box 3, Folder 99, Reel 3U)
    - Schonbein, Christian Friedrich, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 99, Reel 3U)
    - Schrauf, Abrecht, 1871 (Box 3, Folder 99, Reel 3U)
    - Sclater, Philip Lutley, 1875 (Box 3, Folder 99, Reel 3U)
    - Scott, William Benjamin, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 100, Reel 3U)
    - Scudder, Samuel Hubbard, 1864-1894 (Box 3, Folder 101, Reel 3U)
    - Sedgewick, Adam, 1847 (Box 3, Folder 101, Reel 3U)
    - Sella, Quintino, 1861 (Box 3, Folder 101, Reel 3U)
    - Selwyn, Alfred Richard Cecil, 1871-1892 (Box 3, Folder 101, Reel 3U)
    - Seward, William Henry, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 101, Reel 3U)
    - Shelley, Samuel T., 1869 (Box 3, Folder 101, Reel 3U)
    - Silliman, Benjamin, (*), 1834-1856 (Box 3, Folder 102, Reel 3U)
    - Silliman, Benjamin Jr., 1855; 1859 (Box 3, Folder 103, Reel 3U)
    - Silliman, Carrie R., undated (Box 3, Folder 104, Reel 3U)
    - Silvestri, Horace, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 105, Reel 3U)
    - Somerville, Mary Fairfax, 1860 (Box 3, Folder 105, Reel 3U)
    - Spring, Walter Victor, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 105, Reel 3U)
    - Stanton, Timothy William, 1894-1895 (Box 3, Folder 105, Reel 3U)
    - Steenstrup, Johannes Japetus Smith, 1868 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Stevens, Henry, 1869-1870 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Stevenson, J., 1891 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Stimpson, William, 1852-1855 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Suess, Edward, 1874-1887 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Sumner, William Graham, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Swedish Geological Society, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Szabo, Jozsef, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 106, Reel 3U)
    - Tanbini, [ ____ ] (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Teall, Jethro Justinian Harri, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Thacher, Thomas Anthony, 1869 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Thompson, W., 1846 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Thomson, James, 1874-1884 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Torell, Otto, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Trumbull, James Hammond, 1883 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Tyndall, John, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 107, Reel 3U)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 108, Reel 3U)
    - Upham, Warren, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 109, Reel 3U)
    - Vattemare, Alexandre, undated (Box 3, Folder 109, Reel 3U)
    - Verneuil, Edouard, 1848, undated (Box 3, Folder 109, Reel 3U)
    - Volpicelli, Paolo, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 109, Reel 3U)
    - vom Rath, Gerhard, 1868-1887 (Box 3, Folder 110, Reel 3U)
    - von Decken, H., 1885 (Box 3, Folder 110, Reel 3U)
    - von Kobell, [ ____ ], 1855 (Box 3, Folder 110, Reel 3U)
    - von Schlagintweit-Sakunlunski, Hermann, 1852-1855 (Box 3, Folder 110, Reel 3U)
    - Rudolf Alfred (Box 3, Folder 110, Reel 3U)
    - von Tichermach (?), [ ____ ], 1876-1877 (Box 3, Folder 110, Reel 3U)
    - Wadsworth, Daniel, 1848 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Walcott, Charles D., 1895 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Wallace, (Alfred R.?), 1876 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Walsh, Benjamin D., 1865 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Waltershausen, W., 1853 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Warren, Gouverneur Kemble, 1876 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Warren, John Collins, 1853 (Box 3, Folder 111, Reel 3U)
    - Westerman Brothers, G. and B., 1850 (Box 3, Folder 112, Reel 3U)
    - Westwood, John O., 1837 (Box 3, Folder 112, Reel 3U)
    - Wharton, D., 1888-1889 (Box 3, Folder 112, Reel 3U)
    - White, Israel Charles, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 112, Reel 3U)
    - Whitfield, Robert Parr, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 112, Reel 3U)
    - Whitney, Josiah Dwight, 1862 (Box 3, Folder 112, Reel 3U)
    - Wilkes, Charles, 1840-1846, undated (Box 3, Folder 113, Reel 3U)
    - Williamson, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 114, Reel 3U)
    - Williston, Samuel Wendell, 1894 (Box 3, Folder 114, Reel 3U)
    - Wilson, Henry, 1863 (Box 3, Folder 114, Reel 3U)
    - Wilson, Jacob, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 114, Reel 3U)
    - Wing, Augustus, 1867-1877 (Box 3, Folder 115, Reel 3U)
    - Winthrop, Robert C., 1869-1878 (Box 3, Folder 116, Reel 4U)
    - Wohler, Friedrich, 1375 (Box 3, Folder 117, Reel 4U)
    - Woeikof, Alexander, 1886 (Box 3, Folder 117, Reel 4U)
    - Woodhull, Alfred Alexander, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 117, Reel 4U)
    - Woodward, Henry, 1866-1874 (Box 3, Folder 117, Reel 4U)
    - Wurtz, Charles Adolph, 1852 (Box 3, Folder 117, Reel 4U)
    - Wyman, Jeffries, 1845-1863 (Box 3, Folder 117, Reel 4U)
    - Yale Alumni Association of New York, 1895 (Box 3, Folder 118, Reel 4U)
    - Yale College, Class of 1856 (Box 3, Folder 118, Reel 4U)
    - Yale University, President and Fellows of, 1893 (Box 3, Folder 118, Reel 4U)
  - Lectures, notebooks and miscellanea
    - Lectures
      - Evolution: I, [ca, 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 199, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: II, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 120, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: III, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 121, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: IV, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 122, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: V, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 123, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: VI, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 124, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: VII, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 125, Reel 4U)
      - Evolution: VIII, [ca. 1870-1890] (Box 4, Folder 126, Reel 4U)
      - Geology: notes
        - "Water", XXIII, [ca. 1859-1864] (Box 4, Folder 127, Reel 4U)
        - "Ocean", XXIV, [ca. 1859-1864] (Box 4, Folder 127, Reel 4U)
        - "Fire or Heat", XXV, [ca. 1859-1864] (Box 4, Folder 128, Reel 4U)
        - "Solidification and Crystallization of Rocks", XXVII (Box 4, Folder 128, Reel 4U)
        - "The Contraction of the Globe as a Consequence of Cooling", XXVIII, [ca. 1859-1864] (Box 5, Folder 129, Reel 4U)
        - "Summary and Cosmology", XXX (Box 5, Folder 129, Reel 4U)
      - Inaugural: notes, 1856 February 18 (Box 5, Folder 130, Reel 4U)
    - Notebooks
      - Unites States Exploring Expedition
        - "Sea notes on Crustancea"
          - Part I: A. Orders Decapoda and Schizopoda, 1838-1842 (Box 6, Folder 131, Reel 5U)
          - Part II: B. Orders Amphipoda Isopoda, and Lamipoda, 1838-1842 (Box 7, Folder 132, Reel 5U)
          - Part III: C. Order Entomastraca, 1838-1842 (Box 8, Folder 133, Reel 5U)
        - Memoranda on Crustacea, Vols. I-III (presented to Peabody Museum, Yale University, 1869), undated (Box 9, Folder 133, Reel 5U)
        - New Zealand, Sandwich Islands, Samoa, United States (Oregon), 1840-1841 (Box 10, Folder 134, Reel 6U)
      - United States: general
        - New England and New York
          - No. II - V; index, [ca. 1869-1872 Nov] (Box 10, Folder 135, Reel 6U)
          - No. VII - X, 1874 November - 1877 October (Box 10, Folder 136, Reel 6U)
          - No. XI, XIV (Box 10, Folder 137, Reel 7U)
          - No. XV - XVII, 1882 July - 1884 May (Box 10, Folder 138, Reel 7U)
        - San Francisco and Honolulu, 1887 July (Box 10, Folder 139, Reel 7U)
      - United States: miscellaneous
        - New Haven region, 1879 June - 1880 April (Box 11, Folder 140, Reel 7U)
        - Unidentified, undated (Box 11, Folder 141, Reel 7U)
    - Miscellanea
      - Account books, 1842-1848; 1844-1850 and 1899-1901 (Box 12, Folder 142, Reel 7U)
      - Notes and drawings, undated (Box 12, Folder 143, Reel 7U)
        Scope and Contents
        Includes tracing of Clatsop Prairie, Oregon, from a map by J. Drayton, circa 1838-1842, described in the 1952 Mary Withington catalog of the Yale Collection of Western Americana (p. 59).
      - Notes and drawings, undated (Box 13, Folder 144-145, Reel 7U)
      - Passport, undated (Box 13, Folder 146, Reel 8U)
  - Writings and printed material
    - Writings
      - Bibliography: "Systems of Minerology" (Box 14, Folder 147, Reel 8U)
    - Printed material
      - Articles
        - 1836-1859 (Box 15, Folder 148-163, Reel 8U)
        - 1863-1884 (Box 16, Folder 164-183, Reel 8U)
        - 1885-1894, undated (Box 17, Folder 184-196, Reel 8U)
      - Maps
        - "Geological notes on Town-Maps of Berkshire Co., Mass." by James D. Dana, undated (Box 18, Folder 184-196, Reel 8U)
        - "Geological notes on Town-Maps of Westchester Co., N. Y. and Part of Litchfield, Col, Ct.," by James D. Dana, undated (Box 19, Folder 184-196, Reel 8U)
      - Oversize
        - Awards and certificates
          - Dana, James Dwight, 1836-1895, undated (Box 20, Reel 8U)
          - Dana, Edward Salisbury, 1872-1934 (Box 20, Reel 8U)
- Edward Salisbury Dana, 1872-1947; Series II; .5' (2 boxes)
  This series is arranged in three sections: Correspondence, Printed material and Miscellanea.
  Correpondence is arranged alphabetically by individual.
  Printed material and Miscellanea are arranged by type.
  - Correspondence
    - American Journal of Science, 1925 (Box 21, Folder 197)
    - Awards and certificates, 1874-1929 (Box 21, Folder 198)
    - Dana, Arnold Guyot, 1872-1873 (Box 21, Folder 199)
    - Dana, James Dwight
      See: box 1, folder 27-28
    - Dana, Henrietta Silliman (*), 1872 May-1875 (Box 21, Folder 200-204)
    - DeForest, John Hyde, 1900 (Box 21, Folder 205)
    - Dexter, Franklin B., 1873-1879 (Box 21, Folder 206)
    - Drake Family Pedigree [Silliman], 1893 (Box 21, Folder 207)
    - Fulton, John: to "Miss Dana", 1947 (Box 21, Folder 208)
    - Geological Society of London, 1888 (Box 21, Folder 209)
    - Green Mountain Club, 1932 (Box 21, Folder 210)
    - Hayden, Fred S. (copy), 1873 (Box 21, Folder 211)
    - Hillard, H. R., 1892 (Box 21, Folder 212)
    - Kaiserliche Mineralogische Gesellschaft zu St. Petersburg, 1885 (Box 21, Folder 213)
    - Keogh, [ ____ ], 1921 (Box 21, Folder 214)
    - Litchfield, H. E., 1918 (Box 21, Folder 215)
    - Miscellaneous, 1872-1874, undated (Box 21, Folder 216)
    - Nasini, R., 1901 (Box 21, Folder 217)
    - Panebianco, Ruggero, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 218)
    - Rawson, Edward K., 1896 (Box 21, Folder 219)
    - Sracchi, A. (?), 1873 (Box 21, Folder 220)
    - Taft, William Howard, 1911 (Box 21, Folder 221)
    - Zittel, Karl Alfred, 1901 (Box 21, Folder 222)
  - Printed Material
    - German, 1872-1873 (Box 21, Folder 223-224)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 21, Folder 225)
  - Miscellanea
    - Account Book, 1872-1874 (Box 22, Folder 226)
    - Diary, 1875 July - September (Box 22, Folder 227)
    - notebook of Canoe trip, 1881 July - August (Box 22, Folder 228)
    - Account of trip along British Colombia Coast, [ca. 1881] (Box 22, Folder 229)
- James Dana, 1814-1818; Series III; .75' (1 box)
  This series contains a single account book, 1814-1818.
  - Account Book: Utica, New York, store, 1814-1818 (Box 23, Folder 229)
- Maria Trumbull Dana, [ca. 1877-1961]; Series IV; 0.25; (1 box)
  This series is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Articles
    - "United States Exploring Expedition, 1838-1842", undated (Box 24, Folder 230, Reel 9U)
    - "Hillhouse Avenue", [ca. 1930-1861] (Box 24, Folder 231, Reel 9U)
  - Clippings
    - Dana, James Dwight, [ca. 1877-1910] (Box 24, Folder 232, Reel 9U)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1935; 1958 (Box 24, Folder 233, Reel 9U)
    - Dana, James Dwight re: his death, 1895 (Box 24, Folder 234, Reel 9U)
- Additions (not microfilmed)
  Custodial History
  Add. 1984 Jun. Transferred from Kline Biology Tower, 1984 Jun 4 (removed from Insecta Moderenia )
  - ALS to James Dwight Dana from Thomas Vernon Wollaston, 1858 (Box 25, Folder 235)
- Additional materials, 1764-1967; Accession 2004-M-026
  This accession consists of correspondence, memorabilia, printed materials, and photographs of the Dana family, including material relating to the allied Bristol, Brown, and Silliman families. Categories of personal papers, photographs, and books are arranged alphabetically by personal name.
  - Personal papers
    - Dana, Edward Salisbury (1849-1935)
      - Diary and sketchbook [probably of Edward S. Dana] (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Marriage license [to Caroline Bristol], 1883 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Memorabilia
        - Letter opener [shell from New Zealand, gift from James Dwight Dana], 0 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Yale Bicentennial Medal, 0 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Dana, James Dwight (1813-1895)
      - Letter from Charles Darwin, 1859 December 30 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Memorabilia
        - Bookplate [belonging to either James D. Dana or Edward S. Dana], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Cuff buttons and mechanical pencil, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Dana, James Dwight (born 1889), correspondence concerning Bristol family history, 1952 September 8 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Dana, Maria Trumbull
      - "A Brief Record of Gold Selleck and Mary Fish Silliman, Parents of Benjamin Silliman, From Original Sources, compiled by Maria Trumbull Dana, a Great Granddaughter" [typescript], undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Memorials, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - "Prayers of Peace," by ------ Stevenson [inscribed to Maria from Carrie], 1912 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Dana, Mary (May) Bristol (1886-) (Mrs. Alexander Cushing Brown)
      - Acknowledgements of gifts given to Yale University, 1940 December, 1949 December (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Diary with poetry from "Farmington Days", 0 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Wedding present registry, 0 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Dana family, general information
      - Lineal descent from Priscilla Mullins and John Alden, [ca. 1949] (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - James Dwight Dana House, 1962, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - "Story of the Famous Old Willow Ware Plate" [handwritten inventory of housewares], 1924 April (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Allied families
      - Bliss, William, Phi Beta Kappa key, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Bristol family memorial addresses
        - Bristol, John Wolcott, 1922 May 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - Bristol, Louis H., 1910 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Trumbull, Jonathan Jr., correspondence to Joseph Trumbull (brother), 1764 February (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Books and pamphlets by members of the Dana family
    - Dana, Elizabeth Ellery, The Dana Family in America. Boston, Massachusetts: Wright & Potter Printing Co., 1956 (Box 2)
    - Dana, Henrietta Silliman, "Hillhouse Avenue from 1809-1900." New Haven: The Tuttle, Morehouse & Taylor Company. [reprint] (Box 2)
    - Dana, James Dwight, New Text-Book of Geology. New York: Ivison, Blakeman, Taylor, & Co., 1863 (Box 2)
  - Books and pamphlets about members of the Dana and allied families
    - "Benjamin Silliman, Jr.—Educator and Oilman" [commemorative remarks], [ca. 1955] (Box 2)
    - Cornelius, Charles O., "Some Early American Doorways." Bulletin of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, vol. 22, no. 10., 1927 October (Box 2)
    - Dwight, Timothy, "Professors W. D. Whitney and J. D. Dana: Commemorative Address before the Graduates of Yale University, June 23, 1895." New Haven: The Tuttle, Morehouse & Taylor Company. (Box 2)
    - "Edward Salisbury Dana: Editor, January, 1875-June, 1835." Reprinted from American Journal of Science, vol. 30. [2 copies], 1935 September (Box 2)
    - Fisher, George P., Life of Benjamin Silliman. New York: Charles Scribner and Co., 1866 (Box 2)
    - Fulton, John F. and Elizabeth H. Thomson, Benjamin Silliman, 1779-1864: Pathfinder in American Science. New York: Henry Schuman., 1947 (Box 2)
    - Gilman, Daniel C., The Life of James Dwight Dana. New York: Harper & Brothers., 1899 (Box 2)
    - "Memorial Addresses at the Unveiling of the Bronze Statue of Professor Benjamin Silliman, at Yale College, June 24, 1884." New Haven: Tuttle, Morehouse & Taylor., 1885 (Box 2)
    - Schuchert, Charles, "Memorial of Edward Salisbury Dana." Proceedings of the Geological Society of America. [2 copies], 1935 (Box 2)
    - Wilson, Leonard G., ed., Benjamin Silliman and His Circle: Studies on the Influence of Benjamin Silliman on Science in America. New York: Science History Publications., 1979 (Box 2)
    - Wing, Donald G., "New Light on Benjamin Silliman." The Yale University Library Gazette, vol. 31, no. 1., 1956 July (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Bristol, John W., undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Dana, Edward S., 1915 March (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Dana, James Dwight
      - Portrait painted by Daniel Huntington [reproduction and photograph], 1857 May (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Portrait photograph, [1895] (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Dana house at 24 Hillhouse Avenue (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Photograph album [compiled by Mary Dana], 1899 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Yale and Yale reunions [loose album pages], 1903-1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Individual and group portraits [presumably the Dana family, taken at Edgehill, 8 handpainted lantern slides], undated (Box 4)